hey this is the Brandon Sanderson 2025
writing lecture series we are on plot
week two here so today this is more of a
survey class meaning I'm going to go
across a bunch of different methods
people use for plotting their stories
I'm going to talk briefly about each one
uh these are tools for you to do further
investigation on and to try out yourself
I'm not going to go too in depth in any
of them but hopefully something in here
Sparks with you in a way to help you
make your stories have a stronger plot
all right welcome to writing science
fiction
fantasy that that was some only
moderately enthusiastic Applause I I
sense that the semester is well
underway and it's still January and
you're like man this is wait it's still
January that's kind of like the theme of
January in Utah it's still January and
then Fe February arrives and you're like
it's still
January uh we're going to talk about
plot today our second one so the idea
this week is last week we kind of talked
about philosophy of plot the idea of
progression and payoffs and of course
promises today we're going to look at
some models that people use for plot uh
Each of which being ones I have tried in
the past when I've been working on
stories so I can talk about about them
in a an educated way um we can't spend a
lot of time on any one of them uh
because of this this is ooh ooh was that
a no it wasn't a phone call sometimes I
answer it if it's a phone
call doesn't happen as often anymore
everyone's phones are on silent um for
the longest time my um you could I could
go and do all sorts of pranks on my wife
by changing her ring tones but nobody
uses ring tones anymore
except um but yeah so we can't delve
deeply into any of these um I can give
you a survey of different types of plot
structures and why they might work for
you as we talked about um in the first
day you need to be doing this yourself
uh I would recommend trying some of
these particularly if you're having
problems in this area if you're not
maybe you don't need to try them maybe
you've already fig figure out your own
thing so uh there's a smattering um of
these that are uh dealing with um more
Discovery writing ideas and some that
are structured to hang a story on uh
neither once again is necessarily a
better method than another to write a
story the best method to write a story
is the one that makes you consistently
produce the type of thing that you want
to be producing uh up to your current
skill level all right so uh this first
point on here is just to give you a
reminder um of of what you're looking
for in a plot a plot is there to provide
conflict um I don't know if you uh if
you you heard this adage um back in
um in school you know back in your high
school days I did uh the whole the adage
of the king died is not a story it's a
fact the king died and then the queen
died of grief is a story
either of them neither of them are
actually stories but the idea is that
the conflict and the struggle is what
makes a story not the sequence of a of
facts events aren't a story The Struggle
and what's happening to the characters
emotionally and through their character
arcs as they uh work with that struggle
that is what makes a story so you are
looking for conflict you're looking for
ways to show progress to The Reader
through your plot that things are
happening it can be progress can be
regressive right the status quo is
changing facts are being learned other
things you know like characters can be
backsliding and that counts as progress
for a story uh Breaking Bad is all about
some backwards progress right uh and
that uh works very well it's just a kind
of inverse but we would consider that
story progress because your goal as an
author is to show the slide backward so
you're going forward in the story as the
character is sliding back backward um
there's a there's a little adage that I
have that can help you um with figuring
out how you can kind of turn events into
plot lowercase p plot as we're talking
about it and that's the think of um when
you're coming up with obstacles your
obstacles
should
force reinforce or show failure in
growth in some way right
growth of the character growth of the
story if an obstacle doesn't do those
things then what you might have added to
your story is just an event to have
happen and too many of those it stops to
feel like a story stops feeling like a
story um you want them again I'll go
through that again you want them to
force growth in some way in the
character or in the plot you want them
to reinforce something that's been
learned perhaps you have had a little
bit of um a downtime where character's
talking and character had a breakthrough
and then you have an obstacle that can
reinforce that this character has
actually learn something or that this
clue actually matters and is is
relevant or you want the obstacle to
show failure that a character is not yet
ready to overcome their problem to
highlight what is going on with that
problem or you know the characters are
not yet ready to face Darth Vader um and
so the obstacle is Darth Vader has
showed up um the way you overcome it in
the story is Obi-Wan Kenobi steps in and
stops him but then the characters aren't
ready to face him so obiwan Kenobi dies
and so it's an escalation growth is
being forced upon the characters because
they no longer have their um the the
wise Mentor same thing happens in Lord
of the Rings face something they're not
ready for wise Mentor dies you've gotten
through it but it's going to force grow
growth on the characters cuz now the
person that's kind of been keeping them
all together isn't there to keep them
together
anymore so think of obstacles as having
a purpose in your story other than just
being entertaining in themselves and
maybe that will help you to start to use
events to become
plot um the first one we'll talk about
on here is um I I've started using uh
Dan harman's Story Circle instead of uh
the monomyth um D Haron famous writer it
is just a simpler way to look at the
monomyth uh the monomyth you guys I
should say um Joseph Campbell's hero the
Thousand Faces the um the uh the hero's
journey right um and Dan Harman I found
a few years ago has boiled this down
really well into simple principles that
makes sense um and so you can just
Google Dan Harman Story Circle um and
you will get the same image that I like
to reference when uh when going with
this and so the
idea let's talk about the hero's journey
so there's this famous book here with a
thousand faces Joseph Campbell um I
learned in my folklore classes that
folklorists do not like here with a
thousand faces very much um or at least
they're more critical of it uh than pop
culture is uh folklorists look at Joseph
Campbell and say uh um going back to Dr
Thurby who was uh who taught my senior
course she's like this is great in some
ways but it doesn't reference the
sources it uh tends to use other
people's work without uh without saying
that it did it works way too hard to
prove its point and ignores
counterpoints to it um and it pretends
women don't exist um not odd for books
written during that period um but
they're just you know I mean Cinderella
follows the hero's journey but it sure
doesn't talk about that very often uh
and things like this I think of those
for this class's purpose because we're
not a folklore class knowing that here
at the Thousand Faces tries too hard is
a really useful thing to know I have
read the book and I agree lots of
interesting things in there but the idea
that every story and or almost every
story can be can be put in this same
rubric um I think is going tooo far and
in fact I think that for
writers anything I talk about today
could potentially be
destructive because if you treat any of
these Frameworks as Sacro SCT if they
start to become a um if you start to
become a cook instead of a chef if you
look at each piece of this and say well
I have to have that then you can
actually do things that don't match your
story very well and my classic example
those who have who have watched these
lectures before know that I go back to
this well because it's such a perfect
one um is George
Lucas uh George Lucas is a legit genius
um Star Wars to this day is just like we
will probably reference it today I often
do um and he was an amazing he is but
when he was working on Star Wars he's
kind of pass on that along Amazing World
Builder uh really good leader innovative
technology um and all of these things um
he also loved he with a thousand faces
loves here with a thousand faces I
shouldn't speak of Mr Lucas in the past
tense it's just it feels like he has
he's gone more into his retirement and
has let other people take his thing so
it feels more like he's this you know
benevolent patriarch who's like go off
and tell your own stories now kids
um and so but he loves hear the Thousand
Faces you can find lectures he's given
on it PBS specials where he's talked
about it um and you know he obviously
really was deeply influenced by uh that
book and he used it to great effect in
his
storytelling but then he also turned it
into a checklist this is my opinion but
I was there I was there
um I was suddenly we're bouncing between
Lord rings and uh um when when men
failed um I was there hey guys um I was
there opening night for Phantom medas I
am
old okay opening night I didn't have to
wait in line because my dumb Friends
waited in line for me and I got to show
up last minute and just they gotten a
seat for me so uh that was Dan and Peter
uh both who now work for me
uh yeah um but uh and Ben if you know
Ben um so my friends waited in line we
went opening night people were I mean
they had basically everybody had
lightsaber but me uh I like Star Wars
but I wasn't wear bring a lightsaber to
Star Wars uh level of like Star Wars um
and so I know that fan and Menace went
over pretty well for that audience that
day um the
man did this secretly suck all along it
didn't happen until after a little wise
ways like you know and then the internet
reevaluated and decid it was awesome and
that's still baffling to me
but I was also there when if you haven't
seen this movie um
when Luke Skywalker Darth Vader's mom
says spoiler I there's mom um says oh
there was no dad he was just born of the
force and I watched the entire audience
go oh that's a
thing entire audience that otherwise was
swinging their lightsabers and enjoying
things like at that moment they're
like wait Anakin space
Jesus what well years later I was
studying here at 1 thousand faces and I
get to the point where the Virgin birth
is a big part of the monomyth and the
hero's journey uh going back to this
idea of born of the Gods um it wasn't
always the Virgin birth but it was like
the Divine parrot right uh so that Lucas
who had built his whole framework around
the monomyth is like well I need to
include this element in order to make it
fit the hero's
journey and I think it personally was a
step too far um now you know we're we're
not here to criticize one of the great
storytellers of our time too much but I
want to point out that the possible
failing that you can have
anytime a structure becomes too
rigid for you as a writer that you start
to use even the outline that you have
designed to the point that it negatively
impacts your story if it becomes too
rigid if it can't be flexible enough if
it doesn't match your story after you're
into your story be willing to throw Ro
away and that's kind of my um my kind of
cautionary tale for the heroes journey
in all of them but especially the heroes
Journey um 3x structure to an extent too
if you read save the cat you'll be like
all right on page 16 I need to include
this um you're writing Pros uh you're
writing stories um some of the things
that apply to Hollywood don't apply to
us and no one's going to look and see if
you have exactly the 2/3 point a certain
thing happened um I don't think that
even really happens in Hollywood to the
extent that people imagine but we'll get
there so what is the hero's journey well
the hero's journey is this idea um that
stories often fit into a certain
framework that is circular it's why it's
the story Circle the idea is that a
person in a state of
ignorance and kind of believes the world
is perfect um or that you know that uh
their their life will never change they
don't have to think it's perfect but
their life will they they'll think their
life will never change is forced onto an
adventure where they travel and certain
things happen to them to which point
they then return to where they started
uh a better person having made their
entire Society better in some way um
it's the idea of the child becoming the
adult um and it it focuses on this idea
that you you you start at the top of the
circle right um and you start with this
idea of there's a person kind of at a
state of rest either they don't want to
be at a state of rest or they really
like it it can be Bilbo who's like all I
want to do is eat my food smoke my pipe
and uh not cause problems unless it's
for certain people that annoy me right
or it can be Luke Skywalker is like my
life will never change I want to be up
in the stars but my life but I'm but the
reality is here is I'm on the ground and
my life will never change right um that
character is projected forward by a
certain sort of need or requirement that
they don't feel that they're able to
fulfill and they resist in some way um
this is we will use Star Wars um I said
I was going to we use it right here Luke
um is like you know learns about the
Jedi gets offered a lightsaber and is
like no I'm rejecting this I said I
wanted Adventure but but that's not
actually my life um which is then
propelled into being forced to go into
the into the world right by some event
they call it crossing the threshold
usually um something happens that there
is a point of no return uh you see this
in threea structure um as well a lot of
people say in Star Wars this is when
Luke gets back and his aunt and uncle
are dead and he knows he's being hunted
and he cannot return to that life that
life has ended um and so um you then go
on what's called by Campbell the road of
Trials uh a very simple way to explain
all of the first half of act two just a
little thing of now our story happens um
but the road of Trials is the character
is tested in certain ways learns that
they lack the knowledge or skill to S to
conquer those challenges
so that an awareness can be can happen
as eventually prop propelled to a
meeting with divinity of some sort uh
you can just call it a come to Jesus
moment or you can call it a face-
to-face um you know like direct
confrontation with the darkness inside
of you um you know it's this is often in
Star Wars the where he goes into the the
pit underground and sees Darth Vader he
cuts off Darth Vader's head and his face
is there this is is this idea of the the
hero needs to kind of confront um
usually a father figure of some sort or
a parental figure uh you know a deity of
some sort and needs to be transformed
paying some price to gain and Joseph
Campbell calls it The Elixir the
knowledge the skill um or whatever it is
um then the you you emerge from that the
master of Two Worlds both the spiritual
world and the physical world um you know
Luke becomes a Jedi he Masters the
spiritual and it lets him use a laser
sword to cut people's heads off master
of Two Worlds um right and then by
fulfilling that the hero returns home in
some way bringing this knowledge and
bringing themselves forever changed back
uh back it's so vague it can fit a lot
of stories right how could this be
helpful because it's so vague well
there's a lot of points to this that are
really useful for us to focus on um one
is this idea of a circle stories do tend
to do well if it feels like a character
returns to where they were before at
least a mentally or emotionally even
physically and we can see their progress
we talk about progress and payoff payoff
can simply be I was unable to do this at
the start and now I'm a master of it
suddenly that payoff can be extremely
powerful um and it it it really gets
into this idea of the hero's journey is
about learning and obtaining things that
you need but you don't quite know it yet
or you're not willing to reach for it
yet
um tons of people have written way more
on the hero's journey we're not going to
go too much more into it here it is a a
valuable tool I don't like to use it
very much um I find it just a little
to I don't know um I like a little more
flexibility um than I get in the hero's
journey but there's definitely some
elements to it questions thoughts uh
things you want to bring up before we
move on uh to some Discovery writing
methods um is it just as bad to get
sucked into the idea of not following it
too slavishly uh is it just as bad it
depends on if this helps you WR uh the
question is is it just as bad to get to
determinedly say I'm not going to do the
hero's journey um I mean a great deal of
literary fiction rather than commercial
fiction is based around the idea of how
can I tell a story that lacks any of the
identifiable structure components that
generally make a story and there have
been plenty of successful uh literary
fiction pieces that have done that the
thing is a lot of these structures are
so vague that that intentionally
disobeying them you'll get done and
they'll people be like oh here's your
here's your structure it just is right
there you just did it a slightly
different way it's a little bit how like
tolken was like Lord of the Rings is not
an allegory for anything and then
everyone's like this really feels like
World War I in a lot of ways and he's
like
no no allegory they're like yeah but
were you in World War I and he's like
well yes but not an allegory um right
like if you're you're like I'm not going
to use Hero Journey and then someone
comes to you and says well yeah but your
character learns
something you're like oh well that's
part of the hero's journey yeah that's
why the hero's journey is a little bit
vague hero's journey is characters learn
stuff and get better um and so yes you
can indeed tell a story that doesn't
follow any of these beats but I would
not be slavish about it unless you
really want to do an art piece and you
can really figure out how to do it
mostly tell the story that you want to
tell and don't stress too much if it
shares uh some DNA with other things is
there a way to incorporate it so that
the characters progress like even if
they go up at some points like in the
end it's negative yeah if if they is
there a way to incorporate so at some
points they go up at the end it's
negative I mean Star Wars does this with
Anakin right so obviously yes um the the
idea um of that is like is your progress
the character backsliding or is your
progress more of a Greek tragedy
which Campbell does talk about a ton
which are at the end a lot of Greek
tragedies are the character refusing to
like take one of the last steps uh in
rejecting the last step and therefore
because of it it becomes a tragedy
instead um the character you know has
refused the Elixir the character has
refused to return uh and then they die
usually um or something like that so um
so it is totally possible to to have a
negative spin on this and still have it
the framework work really well um and I
would I would say that a lot of stories
uh do that like um I'm I'm on record
multiple times saying I think this is
the structure that uh that Pat rfus is
going to use uh when he's writing the
Name of the Wind Trilogy if we ever get
the third one which I'm confident we
will I I know Pat Uh he no one wants
that book to get done more than him I
believe I've said that before but I
think this is a this is a classic Greek
tragedy a a tragic flaw in a character
that they're highlighted over and over
again during the road of trials that
they refuse to let go of uh to the point
that it causes disaster rather than uh
returns to save the day so um yeah uh
we'll go here and then there and then
we're going to go on to the next one so
how like often is it done or like
feasible would it be to like Shain and
layer multiple like Heroes Journeys like
together yeah how feasible is it to
chain uh layer multiple I would say very
feasible um I think you can argue again
uh one of the reason Star Wars is so
good is because I think it's doing the
sort of thing that you do with a series
in
particular movie one which is actually
movie four but you know whatever movie
one is uh is its own Circle but it is
also the first
Act of a Trilogy in which Luke has only
just if you kind of watch that movie at
the end he's accepted the calling to be
a Jedi and you can argue that that is
him crossing the
threshold of Point number three on the
hero's journey while he's already
crossed the threshold and done the
entire Journey he's now flying home and
you know getting a medal and things like
that but really he's only accepted
point1 and now he's going to have to go
do the road of Trials again in a larger
way end with belly belly of the whale
right facing the father and things like
this so that movie two brings us back to
he's actually failed he needs to do this
again and this time face the father and
return with the Elixir and in this case
you can argue that the Elixir is you
know the idea that he has made the world
a better place he has redeemed the
father uh rather than him becoming the
Father the fathers become him right
that's the whole thing of the original
trilogy and he returns triumphant then
from that road of Trials so right you
you basically got the hero's journey one
Loop one and then a failure and then
again and then it's then uh succeeding
and it works really really well and you
can be doing it with multiple characters
right the idea is to remember your whole
idea of um of conflict and progress what
is your progress how are you signaling
that progress is getting made in Star
Wars there's all these sign posts of
Luke needs to be a Jedi that is the full
Arc he needs to not only be a Jedi he
needs to redeem his father revenge is
what you think the first movie is and
then later it becomes Redemption um and
that's sign posted all the way through
your capital P plot is destroy the Death
Star but your actual story is Luke needs
to be a Jedi and that's what his calling
is and that's what a lot of his progress
is about face the father become a Jedi
uh change the father to be to be you all
right last question there yeah how do
you how do you use this without being
troby
that start to become yeah yeah when does
trop start to become a problem um so
this is going to depend on your own kind
of balance of these things right it's an
excellent question to be asking um every
story will have
tropes and there is a certain Madness to
trying to avoid all
tropes um because every story has them
and and if you are working really hard
and building a identity around the
person who doesn't use the
tropes then you're gonna have a bad time
right you really are because you'll be
like wow this had no tropes and then you
go and you'll read and you'll realize
that you've just done them just
different once because certain things
work for stories it's like how um this
isn't a Trope but um I wrote the the
book mbor right which has this this
really engaging magic system that I
loved where people are like you know
pushing off of coins and flying around
I'm like this is the most original thing
ever and I submit it to my writing group
like this is so cool it's just like
Magneto you're like well there was four
years of my life to write Magneto but
worse right uh mistborn Magneto but
worse
uh and to focus too much on that is
maddening um because uh the truth is
that yeah they share some attributes but
the stories are different and the story
that you're telling the more you write
the better you'll be at finding your own
voice most people I know their first
book it's over the line into using too
many of the tropes and your influences
are a little too obvious but at the same
time right like Lion King is hand H
let they don't care that it's Hamlet I
don't care that it's Hamlet other than
from an academic uh presentation it's a
really great story um and they did it
their own way uh and so I would say to
you practice and stress this less than
you think you need to it's a bigger deal
in first books than it ever is in second
books and later on you start mastering
your influences rather than uh just
unconsciously using them and which point
you'll be able to say wow I really like
this let me figure out what I like about
it and use it I really like the hero's
journey how can I do something
interesting and new with the her journey
you just told saw saw me talk through
the person who probably worships
Campbell the most in pop media that I
know of is Lucas and even his use of it
in those that original trilogy is really
interesting and does some very cool
things with it that U makes the
structure of Star Wars fascinating even
though you know hey he's hitting all
these points you can do things like that
um and even these days like it depends
on your genre I get I get kind of like
horrified by the way that certain genres
approach
tropes where there's Tik Tok and they'll
be like here's the five tropes that make
my story and that's really appealing to
some readers um those uh some people who
like certain romance novels did I
mention this already you can go to the
Amazon page and it'll say this is a
happily ever after with no cheating uh
and none of like it'll list the things
that don't occur in it right and what do
and that's like before the
summary so that the reader knows that
you know they they can throw away this
book if it doesn't match uh before they
even you know like um that kind of
horrifies me as a as a reader because
that's not how I approach uh reading but
that works for a lot of people so the
answer is don't stress this too much
find your own uh your own path but
particularly if it's your first book you
could do way worse than leaning hard on
one of these structures and going too
hard on them uh you'll find that in
character and World building you will
stretch further naturally and in so
doing make the story your own okay um
let's start talk about yes but no and
so this is another famous one that I
believe comes from Hollywood
originally um and this is the idea that
stories are a series of escalating
incidents not just incidents and that
escalation causes progress a natural
sense of progress because it can only
escalate so far before it comes to a
head uh and people using this who are
generally more Discovery writer uh will
will be asking they they'll come up with
with events and then they'll let them
Cascade into one another so they get
more and more in line with the story
you're telling why do I what do I mean
by that well screw ball comedies they
get more and more ridiculous right so
that a story an event happening at the
end at the end of your story to for a
screw bow comedy my wife just made me
watch it's her favorite you know the
characters are in a in a room with like
Mobsters shooting at them um with top
secret plans and with like rocks you now
tell what this is that uh that can like
that that are harmonic and everyone's
shooting each other and there's
millionaires there and it starts with
just a guy on a business trip with his
fiance you spiral further and further
out of control to where the point that
the ridiculous events at the end don't
seem outlandish because they were small
steps that got you there um if you're
escalating not in a screwball comedy
it's escalating Stakes uh you could
we'll use Star Wars again because
everybody knows Star Wars it starts with
I need a Droid it ends with blowing up a
planet well that's no moon um right it
it ends with a military operation
against the Galactic Empire in which our
hero who only needed a Droid is now
blowing up the most destructive space
station in the world and has learned to
be a space
wizard how did that happen small
escalations you go to buy a Droid but
you bought the wrong Droid that Droid
has um has a message in it for somebody
that you know well take the Droid to the
person to let uh the message go okay but
you did that um so let me let me explain
what yes no but and um and yes but no
and yes but noan says you start with a
problem I need a
Droid you ask yourself does the
character solve this
problem uh and the answer in this case
is yes but you know he got the wrong
Droid you could also argue this is no he
got a Droid but it's it's not the Droid
that'll work for him but I think this is
yes but yes but you answer it either
with yes and you add a complication um
or you answer it with no and you add a
complication to start uh spiraling so
yes but it's a it's a secret Droid that
has a a story for um for Obi-Wan Kenobi
all right Kenobi want Kenobi solve the
problem no and you're being hunted by
the Empire and they've killed your aunt
and
uncle great um I need to get off planet
um do we know how to get off PL where to
get off planet yes but uh the guy that
you hire to get you off pled is a
scoundrel who who shot first and is only
interested in money right you can see
how this is so now we're off Planet
you're like all right we just need to
get to this place where we can deliver
the plans and we'll be safe do we get
there no and you get pulled into the
Death Star and there's a giant evil
space wizard Samurai there who killed
your
father um right like you can see how by
the end you're blowing up that's no moon
what whatever it is a giant space
station um yes but no and's whole goal
is to keep you focused on making things
worse and worse and worse um this tends
to work best in
shorter uh shorter
fiction um escalating across a 400,000
word book is a lot more difficult than
escalating across an 80,000 word book
it's a reason why a lot of Thrillers um
tend to be that 80 to 100 range and if
they go longer than that this sort of
constant escalation constant hyper um
you know uh the pacing is so fast
everything's always blowing up someone's
always chasing you um it you run out of
you run out of gas on that stuff um but
it can be a great way to tell a story uh
particularly in the short term you're
like I need to get them from point A to
point B let's do some yes but no and um
and
really escalate some things in small
ways for each of the characters building
this conflict and this tension
particularly if you keep in mind like
the characters problem is this they need
to you know they need to learn to be
more caring do they solve it here no and
this do they solve it here no and this
okay they try a smaller thing does that
work yes but you can see how you can
kind of use this to give your sense of
progress through the course of the the
characterization I'm actually going to
skip over three act and just do the
other one that is really good for
Discovery writers I found um and that's
the the tri fail cycle SL points on the
map is how I like to talk about this one
um this is the method that Robert Jordan
used to write books uh Robert Jordan uh
was a hybrid between an outliner and a
uh Discovery writer but he he veered
toward Discovery writer like he was if
there's a if there's a line he's over
here and you can tell that by when I sat
down um with uh with his wife and with
the owner of the company Tom Dory and
they were reminiscing about the Wheel of
Time and when Robert Jordan went in to
pitch a three book
series uh that was The Wheel of Time for
those who have read it I wrote books
number uh like what 12 13 and 14 to
finish it off right uh and his three
book outline ended with the last part of
book 14 that he had written and left for
me it's not like he just said well we'll
get get there and then add more on top
no it just took him 14 books to get
through the three books because he kept
yes but no ending all the way through he
would call it points on the map though
he'd say I know I'm driving to
Washington DC on a road
trip and I know what what I want to see
in Washington DC right I want to go and
see the Lincoln Memorial that's kind of
the equivalent you saying all right I
know then I'm going to write a book
about this character who has to fight
the dark lord at uh at Mount Doom um for
the fate of the
world and he'd say I also know that
along the way on my road trip metaphor
you know I'm starting in let's say I'm
starting in Utah I know that I want to
see um
um I'm from Lincoln nobody wants to see
Lincoln um but let's pretend I want to
go see Lincoln Nebraska what is it uh
I'm gonna have a Runza Brandon always
talks about how great Runza is so uh
that's the equivalent of uh when Robert
Jordan he pitch the series he said I'm
going to do this cool thing where a
person pulls a sword that's not a sword
from a stone that's not a stone and
everybody doesn't quite realize that
he's a King Arthur uh archetype until
much later on uh because you know the
swords of magic uh a magic you know the
stone is a is a fortress and the sword
is a is this magic item that you need to
magnify your power it's in the shape of
a sword but it's not actually used as a
sword uh so the sword that's not a sword
from the stone that's not a stone um you
know uh he gave that away a little bit
by naming everybody after people from
arthan Legend except for the ones that
aren't are from North's mythology but uh
you know um it works very well in the
story uh so that he knows he wants to
get there right and so he will come up
with this map of the places he wants to
go and that's his outline his outline is
six bullet points character starts here
this big event this big event this big
event this big event this big event at
the end and then he'll be like I'm going
to Discovery right myself between points
one and two and see how long it takes me
and that gives some structure to the
story where you know the big moments so
you can start foreshadowing them
um and despite what JK Rowling says I
think this is how she did Harry Potter
um I don't think she had as much as she
pre she claims she has just being a
writer and knowing um but I do think she
had points on the map I do think she
said I know I'm going here I know this
is going to get revealed I know this is
going to revealed and those things she
foreshadows really well um because it
can really help someone who's Discovery
writing have an ending in mind and be
able to work on some of this progress
and payoff as they go that said do
remember if you are naturally Discovery
writer that you can fix anything in post
uh you can revise your s story so that
you can add all of these things on once
you get to the end revision can do
wonders um so it's okay to not have but
I have found more and more of the
discovery writers I talk to actually use
this why do I call it a trifil cycle uh
this is how Dave Wolverton taught this
kind of same idea in the class when I
took it from him long ago and it's
always one of those points that he
taught that stuck with me uh he said
basically if you don't know how to build
the structure of your story remember
that before something can be
accomplished a character should
generally fail at it at least once in an
Ideal World depending on how hard this
thing is they fail at it twice or three
times and they should try the most
intelligent things you can think
of and do and execute them cleverly and
either fail because of their personal
flaws or you know lack of skill or fail
because they've been out
thunk uh and the villain has already
assumed that someone will try the most
obvious thing that all the readers are
like well why don't you do this
character tries it and fails to prove to
the reader that the that the author has
thought of that and indeed the problem
is bigger than that um it helps a lot
with this you know points on the map um
idea this idea of
yes we need to do this we need to
destroy the Death Star or whatever well
what can we try to destroy the Death
Star that is uh that is intelligent
that's going you know going to work well
we'll we'll send our spies and they'll
get the plans but oh no you know fails
because of this or whatever you know
like this whole idea um that the
characters are being smart but they're
failing because of the intelligence or
power of the villain or because they
just haven't learned enough yet which
lets you do that whole hero shoury thing
right go ahead and that can happen off
screen I mean the Bin's died off screen
yeah the this one's I I was trying to
force this uh uh Star Wars into this
rubric it doesn't fit this one really
well because Rob or because George Lucas
was using a structure right so what
would you do with uh with this I
wouldn't probably use the bin right uh
what I would
do um with this one is the trifil cycle
would be luke learning the force right
so your Tri fail cycles for him are
here's the lightsaber I I know I got to
get back to my family you've just been
offered to be a Jedi you're running home
to power converters but yes he does then
it's like all right you've got the laser
sword but you can't block the things cuz
you're trying to block the things and uh
and you're not good and then it's like
here's Darth Vader Darth Vader Has Come
For You Luke looks and then ob- one
knows he's not ready yet and intervenes
like these are your Tri fail Cycles is
really Luke defeats Vader and then even
at the end Luke doesn't defeat Vader
Luke just takes the first step to
becoming a
Jedi and uh Vader gets you know gets uh
gets yeed as my kids would say um into
the next movie yeah so that's probably a
better version of the trifil cycle learn
to be a Jedi learn to be a Jedi try to
defeat Darth Vader I he fails defeating
Darth Vader in one spectacular way
before he succeeds and has several
little instant along and that really you
know if Luke hadn't faced Darth Vader
got his hand cut off and failed that
whole trilogy would just not be as
successful or as interesting because
that failure taught him uh so much right
obstacles force you to learn if they're
used correctly yeah I feel like in 2025
I I I think this is Cinema's fault but
people always like call things plot
holes that are not really yes oh Cinema
Sins
oh okay what's the happy medium of like
you want to like because you said like
failing at it but where do you find
where's your happy medium so plot holes
and happy mediums all right you'll get
to be next so you can put your hand down
um so the idea is Cinema sin and things
like this people are now hunting for
plot holes I have big problems with the
way that the internet um uh criticism uh
Realm thinks about plot holes um and
this is because a a story cannot lack
plot holes by those definitions right
because a story cannot accurately
represent real life without having
infinite space and time to tell it um
because of that every story must cut
Corners uh every story is going to uh
the best story as well
now what we want to avoid is things that
will kick the majority of readers out of
the story because they are too focused
on asking questions that are not uh
helping you tell your story and those
are two very different things right so
if you think about
it um here I'll give you an example when
I was in college I had a friend who had
a really great metaphor that I still
love to this day he said you want to
avoid gorillas in the phone booth
okay
imagine that an a character is walking
along the uh Street talking on the phone
to his significant other and they're
experiencing a breakup and it's really
tense and then the narrative says and he
passed a gorilla in the phone booth we
don't have phone booths anymore he
passed a gorilla in the Starbucks um
right um and you know and then just kept
on going well some things like that
make it hard to focus on the story that
you're trying to tell because you've
dropped an outof context problem on the
reader uh you we'll have to get you in a
few minutes so wait wait until I'm done
with this out of Contex problem that
Boots the reader out because they're
like but what about the grill in the
phone booth um and this is often a
matter of where do you place these
things and which things kick the
majority of your readers out how many
readers while reading Lord of the Rings
worry about the Eagles and wonder if the
Eagles uh could have flown the ring
right um if a significant number of beta
readers are being kicked out of the
story to be like yeah but the Eagles
like you could see how that could it
never did to me but you could see how
something like that could as you're
reading the story you could be like but
wait this whole story doesn't matter and
in those cases I do recommend that the
author be like we can't do this because
of X sometimes your first try fail cycle
is to get rid of those questions about
pla holes um but normally when you're
writing your story you accept that your
reader will be on board for it and you
tell the story the best way you can and
if a majority of beta readers or Alpha
readers are having a problem with
something then maybe you can address it
this is why we what we call uh it was
from an old stage play ter hang a
lantern on it um they would you know
often times better than having you know
one piece of the stage be poorly made
cuz they had like no time to get it done
they would put a lantern on the part
that doesn't look good and have the
characters note it be like oh yeah that
Lantern doesn't work and never has you
know like whatever so that the reader
can stop worrying about it and instead
of you know there's a grill in the phone
booth you either don't put it there or
say he passed the grill in the phone
booth his friend Charlie was home from
uh you know doing his duty on the street
corner dancing with the sign suddenly
the GR has explained you've got Charlie
introduced it's kind of indicating that
Charlie will be important later on and
so therefore we can get back to the
story you don't need to know who Charlie
is you don't need to know any of that
you just need to know that you're going
to get it answered and hanging a lantern
on it is a I'm going to answer this or
don't think about this don't worry I
thought of it uh sort of thing
um those are the plot holes you should
be worried about the things that are
actively booting your reader um and not
the things that 3 years later someone
says yeah but what about this that you
could explain with a sentence and no one
got bothered by it while they were
actually reading the book okay this is
why Simon is a problem there's usually
like one actual plot hole and then the
rest of the whole thing is
um answers that could be given in one
sentence or half the time that were
given and they just ignore um back here
and then we'll jump over here thank you
uh what about problems for characters
that they like can't solve say loses a
limb and want to go the path of Mag gr
right so the question is um what about
things that characters can't solve like
a character loses limb and you don't
want to go the path of magically regoing
it we will talk in sanderson's laws
during the um during the actual World
building thing about my distinction
between what I call uh a character flaw
uh a character handicap and um I've got
it's in my my notes there's like three
of them one of them is a thing the
character should solve you want them to
uh like a character flaw uh one is a
handicap this is something that by my
definitions they put on themselves that
makes things harder but you don't want
them to overcome such as um such as in
the this terminology would be Superman
handicaps himself by having a moral code
right uh and then there are uh
legitimate challenges to overcome that
are not your fault that the story is not
about you know you fixing but you have
to get around them somehow such as you
know you have lost a limb um but you
know you still need to save the world
how you going to learn to sword fight
now right like those three things are
treated differently by narratives and I
might have different words to Define
them when I actually teach that lecture
because I change it every year all right
um so so there we go all right we'll go
to you and then we're gonna we're going
to keep going okay just super quick
thing yeah is there a way like let's say
you want that gorilla in the foam boo to
stick out like you're purposely putting
it there because you want the reader to
go wait why is there a boo is there a
way to do that wow
keeping plot B together yeah okay you
want the grill the foam Booth how can
you insert that and make the reader
question without so there's a couple
depends on how much of a gorilla it is
uh in a lot of fantasy and science
fiction you can throw out a jargon term
and the reader knows that you're going
to explain what the magic means later on
right they'll say well we can solve that
with XYZ magical thing you don't need an
explanation there at all um if you what
you're really saying will kick the
reader out then you and you want that
then you better make sure that what's
happening next immediately is not
relevant for them to
remember um because you know or you want
to hang in Lantern on it a lot of times
you'll be like he saw a gorill in the
phone booth and and thought I'll deal
with that later
right um you see a lot of narratives do
that with gorillas in the phone booth uh
and sometimes you're that's your story
promise your promise is this story is
weird right um like H guy of the Galaxy
there's a grill in the phone booth like
every few pages right and usually
there's some sort of Watson character in
those you know the person's like can you
explain this no and then they just keep
going um and you know you know that's a
story a lot about yes but no an where
the yes but the butt is always something
weirder than you thought it was and the
end is always something weirder indeed
than you thought it was yeah mhm um so
last week we were talking about my book
um in my writing group and I got the
comment that it's kind of like Wayside
stories which is what I was going for
okay so how do you get it to be
something that feels more like I don't
know writing a middle grade book and I
want it to feel like
um like mysterious and magical but I
also want it to make sense okay so
you're getting the comment that's like
Wayside stories where um the randomness
is the fun of Wayside story right uh and
you want it to feel more magic realism
which is the world is a magical place we
don't have necessarily need or have
explanations for it um boy this is
really individual to your story it's one
of the things that's hard to answer in a
lecture format uh because there's all
kinds of ways that you could solve this
individual problem um in your position
what I would do is I would try to make
the things that happen less of a non
sequer to the characters in the story
usually magic realism there there's some
Wonder to it but they accept that this
is just part of the world um and if
they're like wow that's so wack
um if you have a Watson character being
like wait why why are why why towels
then it makes it more funny um you also
I would look at your diction and is your
diction skewing toward Whimsy and a
little more literary to get you into
that magic realism mode or is your
diction skewing toward kind of a little
bit silly and playful which is going to
um head toward that um some it may not
be as big a problem as you as you think
opening of Harry Potter starts with a
very Wayside story you know a man with
no not enough neck and a woman with too
much neck but then you know ends up but
I mean Harry Potter goes Whimsical
Wayside fairly often and manages to come
back to itself um so middle grade it may
not be a problem but how your characters
react is going to be a part of that um
but there's a 100 ways to solve this
that we can't get into right now so um
all right we're going to move on to
threea structure and I end up 15 after
yeah okay so we're going to go to threea
structure so um threea structure there's
also seveno story structure and
ninepoint story structure um and things
like this they all kind of boil down to
the same idea that starts with the the
Hollywood threea formula um and this is
another one that you can just Google me
on uh and um and you can kind of follow
along um it is a little like the hero's
journey except 3A structure is really
about propelling toward a climactic
explosive
ending um and it is less about the
circle and coming back and it is more
about it's like an arrow pointed at an
explosion um and it is really focused
around the idea of conflict and things
going wrong it works very well once
again uh if you follow the the kind of
formula more strongly it works better
for shorter stories not just short
stories shorter novels um than it does
for longer ones but the whole concept of
Acts and what the First Act means what
the midpoint means um and those things
is really relevant to storytelling all
around so threea format it's
3A it's actually 4A but they like threea
so much they keep it that because the
midpoint really divides the middle act
into two and usually the middle act the
the the film Majors back me up on this
right it it the they're like it's three
acts but the first one the last one are
short the middle one's double length and
has a big bead in the middle you're like
that really feels like four a they're
like no no no yeah the midpoint the most
important Point yes yeah it's kind of
like 4X but it's they call it 3x so your
First Act is where you're going to try
to get most of your Exposition out of
the way in a threea format you're going
to try to introduce a character you're
going to introduce a need you're going
to introduce a status quo um and the um
the the big thing that a lot of people
in Hollywood talk about that I I do
really like is the idea of the what's
the big
question um when I uh one of the so Joe
Russo who um who is one of the directors
of the uh The Avengers films uh among
other things when got a chance to chat
with him about story structure this was
the number one thing he highlighted I'm
like so what's the most important tool
for you in telling stories and Joe said
the dramatic question what is the story
about particularly in relation to the
character what question will this story
answer that he he feels is the the key
to breaking a story he says every story
that he's told um has benefited strongly
from knowing that question upfront
uh this is something that a lot of the
the books on writing screenplays will
talk about they'll call it what do they
call it the the dramatic question
they've got a a term for it it's just
major dramatic question major dramatic
question your major dramatic question um
if it was going to Star Wars thing is
most have multiple but you'd be like
will Luke succeed in becoming a Jedi and
getting Vengeance for his father's death
is probably your major dramatic question
because that question needs to be be act
asked by the end of act one and most
people agree the end of act one for Star
Wars is when he finds his uh his Anon
Uncle dead and he cannot return um it's
again that whole idea of of the hero's
journey so you want to be asking that
question the question needs to be act it
doesn't mean like a lot of um stories in
Yan Jones like the cold open is not act
one right the cold open moving into will
Indiana Jones find the um the Lost
Arc and you know uh that becomes your
dramatic dramatic question at that point
um rather than you know will Indiana
Jones get through this cave that's got
that's full of tarantulas that spin webs
and hang on them for some reason um
yeah um so act one then uh then involves
what they call the inciting
incident uh the inciting in in is not
kind of your like Propel you out of the
um out of Act One into act two uh the
inciting incident is just this this
thing that starts causing a Cascade of
events uh in Star Wars it is probably
Leia and sending the droids you know to
to try to take this story uh this uh
these plans to Obi-Wan Kenobi help me
Obi-Wan K Kenobi you're my only hope
inciting incident droids land because
the droids land Luke's able to find the
droids because Luke finds the droids he
ends up up with Obi-Wan Kenobi because
he's with Obi-Wan Kenobi he's not there
when the Stormtroopers kill his family
because they kill his family he's
required to go with Oban Kenobi to try
and find the princess because he goes
with right the inciting incident is this
thing that starts a Cascade and a lot of
Hollywood formula they like you know
focus on this thing quite a bit um I
don't know if you need one um but uh the
inciting incident um for the way of
Kings is zth killing the King
um and things just start cascading a lot
from that um so let's see I miss
anything yeah there's usually an attempt
a refusal right uh as part of that and
then you hit that uh that plot point at
the end of part one which is life can
never be the same that's called plot
point one and it separates act one from
act two act two I I once had a professor
explain U
that um act one you chase someone up a
tree act two you throw rocks at
them act two is the period of rocks
being thrown at a character and so you
visualize this as things need to get
worse uh everything the characters try
makes the problem worse in somehow uh in
some way and it is called rising action
everything's always getting worse um and
the characters don't don't have the
skill knowledge or what's it to solve
these problems yet this is kind of your
progress right you're identifying like
they they can't solve the problem
because they cannot solve the mystery
because her does not yet have all the
clues to tell him who it would be
therefore
uh um I really
like uh they're good books um but he
can't solve the mystery because he
didn't have the have the answers yet so
he therefore must and the story getting
the answers um while things uh in that
case escalate and a lot of the
escalation in mystery is I thought I had
the answer but I don't am I going to be
able to solve this problem before
there's another murder a lot of times
there is another murder even if there's
not there's this Rising tension of I'm
trapped in an enclosed space someone's
committed a murder my every theory is
wrong is this the case I'll fail um
happens a lot to uh to some to establish
detectives um so then you hit your
midpoint um and your midpoint in
Hollywood structure is your big
twist uh does not have to be a
surprising twist right your big twist
like uh everyone says the midpoint in
Star Wars is they arrive to alderon and
alderon is gone and they get pulled into
the Death Star right suddenly the story
takes on a completely different uh
different feel no longer are we just
getting these plans somewhere we are
sucked into the problem you want either
a major escalation that uh happens as
your midpoint you want a reframing of
the story in some important way or you
want to make it deeply personal to the
main character in some way that it
wasn't before this is called your
midpoint um and it's the point where
everyone who is watching this this the
film were reading the book and was just
a little bit whatever sits up and says
oh um and that again that can be a big
surprise but it doesn't have to be it
can be a big escalation instead um but
in I would say in Hollywood format
that's the most important moment in your
entire story is that reframing and
expansion of it um from there you go
into the second part um of act two where
the attempts to solve the problem are
more frantic and the consequence
of failing become even greater leading
to the characters having tried
everything that they can or that they
think they can and leading them to um oh
what's the it's a famous it's a famous
show that talks about the belly of the
whale or the the darkest the the darkest
moment the point right before act three
where the characters are at their low
points the All Is Lost moment where's
that from it's the All Is Lost moment
someone in a in a movie that gets memd
and clipped and things like that um but
you you generally and this have that all
L moment we tried everything we
could there are no
answers we have failed and then
something they've learned along the way
or accomplished along the way makes them
realize wait no there is one last thing
we could
try and that propels you into act three
where you try you set it up this is the
last chance there is no more trying um
if you fail now it is the end if you
fail now the Death Star will
destroy the rebel base um and the story
you know there's no more story we have
failed and then they either succeed or
fail in a climactic moment that you have
pointed the arrow out from the beginning
in Star Wars once again that arrow is we
have a hole in the Death Star that you
can you know there the plans have a
secret and and then it ends with Luke
exploiting that secret while accepting
his Destiny to become a Jedi by
rejecting technology and embracing
tradition right um and so boom um
literally um you
have you have your climactic moment
um Hollywood formula works pretty well
uh I like it a little bit better than
the heroes juny personally because
partially because everyone has their own
interpretation of it and every essay you
read on Hollywood formula is going to
present it in a different way uh the
Bible of this is a book called save the
cat um but save the cat um is referenced
less often than all the people who
learned from save the cat who made their
own versions of it um and so learning
kind of this this three act this is how
to create a western style story
structured in the way that western style
audiences expect them to happen um you
do not have to at any point follow this
but it is it is the big one yeah we go
here and then over here so my questions
about adaptation yeah the Lord of the
Rings to me I feel like is the
quintessential Discovery story okay yeah
I don't know if you agree with that like
thoughts but but Peter Jackson adopting
it I feel like he's adopted it into this
Hollywood fre act structure where things
happen things happen and then in the
final film they're like well let's go to
the black gate let's let's try and draw
sorrow and out would you would you say
that that's like how do you feel about
like that relationship of like
adaptation yeah from like one one plot
point or one plot device into like this
three act Hollywood and translating in
between that's an excellent question
that might be too big for this class but
I'll give a stab how do I feel about
adaptation um I do feel that um film is
a different medium and you are going to
have to change things to film and I feel
like booked a film where people refuse
to do that often leads to other problems
um there's a reason why I think the
third Harry Potter film is stronger than
the first two and I think it has to do
with a more liberal adaptation to match
the the medium better that said some
we've had a lot and I mean a lot of
people poorly adapting Source material
in the last 10 years as the streaming
boom has happened and that's how we end
up with Master Chief in a romance with a
member of the Covenant where's my halo
homies right like like um it's okay like
you need like when VV made Dune there
are things he decided to cut and some of
them are different from the choices I
would make um like you know like I've
talked about it Movie 2 deciding to um
to half keep the time Jump and half not
leads to some some interesting
storytelling problems for Dune 2 I still
think they're both 10 out of 10 movies
um for a book that is virtually
unadaptable even if you're David Lynch
right um and so like I think that they
have to be different things now
Hollywood is going to Hollywood and you
could make an argument that the Lord of
the Rings as more of an episodic
midcentury um uh you said exploration
story which I'd agree with the hobbits
go here and discover and explore Tom
Bombadil the hobbits go here and explore
and discover this thing and it wasn't
really meant for threea structure it
wasn't even meant to be three books um
that and some there are costs to that
right I think Movie 3 is largely weaker
than Return of the King um as a book
movie 2 is as strong I feel and it
really fit the format well um and he
managed to make Movie 1 and two just
surprisingly strong films making them
fit the format but it didn't work as
well for three but it doesn't matter
because the scenes on Mount Doom between
froto and Sam are just so good that we
forgive him right uh it's okay to have
one n.5 in a Trilogy of tens we'll let
you have that Peter Jackson um but you
know what I'm saying here like I I I'm
not sure that there is a line there
there's a whole Continuum it depends on
the property the person adapting it how
what their passion is and what matches
for the actual story that's being
told uh yeah I promised you I would get
over here did I yes there you are okay I
was just wondering when you were kind of
like I don't know how to say this like
growing up in your writing process like
how aware of like these like reactr
react structors and things like that how
like conscious of them were you as you
were trying to do them um I would say
that I was not uh early on very
conscious the more I grew so let me um
we're going to do this last question
everyone else write your questions down
and I I'll try to get to them next week
but let me let me tell you something I
learned from a video game streamer well
no a card game streamer um I learned
this from a from uh guy named Lis Scott
Vargas who plays Magic the Gathering
yeah um he was talking about how you
learn to be a better player of um a card
game and he says when you learn your
first rules of a card game it is just
really hard to keep those rules in your
mind it's so the board game is so
complex that level one you have to
devote all your attention to to just be
able to remember this is how this card
is played this is the time where I draw
a card the time in a turn where I draw a
card as you play more and more those
things become second nature to you which
leaves room in your brain to level up
and to start focusing consciously on
other things and the better you get the
more that becomes Instinct and you can
then focus on something else writing I
think is the same way as a new writer it
is hard it is super hard perhap the
hardest thing for a writer to learn to
do it
consistently and to just sit down and
write that's all you can often do as a
new writer thinking about all of this if
you try to keep this all in mind will
just overwhelm you and you just won't
get anything done as you build habits
and you're writing more consistently you
can then start to say well what is this
story about and you can start to kind of
ask yourself the kind of great dramatic
question and explore that as you start
to do things like that naturally as you
start to tast naturally figure out where
chapter breaks feel right to you um
these things will become second nature
and you can start to focus on even
higher level and higher level things so
a lot of this right now I'm giving you
as tools to use later on um and
depending on where you are in your
journey or to use as diagnostic tools
for what's going wrong or to help you
build an outline but don't stress
keeping this all in your head as a newer
writer at at the first you will not be
able to and so don't worry about that
worry about what you can do and each
time you feel like you're ready to level
up add something else you're going to
focus on until that starts to become
second nature to you all right uh we're
going to get to the last one here which
is the structure uh uh the um the
structure model using a structure
model
um I really like this one simply because
this allows you to practice your Chef
versus cook structure model is you look
at a Sub sub genre you're not looking at
like Adventure you're not even even
really looking at uh necessarily you
know spy movies you're looking at a
specific kind of heist you're like I'm
going to identify all of these books
that I love that do this specific kind
of heist and I'm going to take it and
use it in a science fiction story this
is the I love Hamlet what's great about
Hamlet what other stories do revenge
stories uh about a a you know a a person
restoring themselves to their father's
Throne like who else has done this what
can I do with this and you spend a lot
of time kind of researching these and
you build out the points that work
really well that don't all have to be
there but that you know are points along
the way and you start adapting that your
story I don't have a lot of time to go
in this one but this is one of the ones
I use for the way of Kings I used the
same so so
hooers and um miracle and all these
Underdog Sports stories are the same
story as Ender Game which is the same
story of the bridge crew
in uh way of Kings Underdog Sports story
Pitch Perfect and way of kings use the
same plot structure
okay right when you can learn what makes
those plot points work and what makes
like the stakes are much bigger in way
of Kings I don't think they're getting
executed in uh Pitch Perfect very often
but the idea of we've got we've got a
team who are you know it's uh Cool
Runnings nobody's good at what they're
supposed to be doing and there's a coach
who can come in and get them all focused
and get them pointed in the right way
way so that they can pull off the
impossible that's a type of plot
structure that I identified and said I
like this why do I like this what makes
this really work and I spent years kind
of reading these things watching these
things building what points I think work
to the point that I could take that and
I could use it as a structure to tell
part of a giant Epic Fantasy story in a
way that worked really well because I
knew I could see the whole plot
structure really easily because I'd seen
it done so many times and I could then
make it my own um this is a really great
method if particular if you're having
trouble with plot and you are even if
you're a discovery writer you're like I
am just going to watch a bunch of these
build a plot that that the points of
them that I like I'm going to ignore the
dumb ones I don't like the plot points
and I'm going to you adapt that into a
new medium particularly if you like take
you know it to a new medium or a new
aesthetic and I'm going to tell my story
with that structure can be a great way
to springboard yourself into uh telling
a great story uh that is our lecture for
today uh thank you all for coming and we
will next week do a Q&A on
[Applause]
plot for